A Guide to the Rives Family Papers, 7/24/2002
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Rives Family Papers, 1820-1875
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4331
This collection consists of ca. 80 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased on 1953 July 9.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of correspondence letters, business and legal papers of the Rives Family. Correspondents include Alexander Brown, James P. Henderson, Samuel Pannill, Alexander Rives, Cornelia Rives, Elizabeth Pannill Rives, Margaret Cabell Rives, Robert Rives, Jr., William Cabell Rives,
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Alexander Brown to Robert Rives, Jr.
    - Alexander Brown, Belmont, to Robert Rives, Oakland 1844 Mar 6
      -- re an account for a wagon, made out and price fixed by Mr. Cocke; family illnesses
    - Alexander Brown, Belmont, to Robert Rives, Oakland 1845 Sep 29
      -- re an account concerning Mrs. Vaughan and Mr. William M. Ewen
    - Alexander Brown, Belmont, to Robert Rives, Oakland 1854 Mar 2
      --re accounts with Mr. Harris and Mr. Ewen
  - James P. Henderson to Margaret C. Henderson, with a copy of his will
    - James P. Henderson to Mrs. Margaret "Minna" C. Henderson, Blair Park 1835 June 30
      -- re "an abominable and unpardonable lie about the furniture" that he had told
    - James P. Henderson Last Will and Testament, with note to Mrs. [John T.] Cocke and note from John T. Cocke (July 9, 1835) about the will at the end 1835 June 30
  - Samuel Pannill to Robert Rives, Jr.
    - Samuel Pannill, Campbell County, to Robert Rives, Jr., Warren 1849 July 28
      -- probability of cholera in Albemarle; William Pannill's visit to "Oakland," Warren
    - Samuel Pannill, Green Hill, Campbell County, to Robert Rives, Jr., Warren 1851 Aug 20
      -- corn and tobacco crops; disgust with convention
    - Samuel Pannill, Green Hill, Campbell County, to Robert Rives, Warren 1851 Dec 25
      -- book prices; family news
    - Samuel Pannill, Green Hill, to Robert Rives, Jr. 1858 Jan 15
      -- crops, prices, etc.
    - Samuel Pannill, Green Hill, to Robert Rives, Jr. and family 1858 Apr
    - Samuel Pannill, Green Hill, to Robert Rives, Jr. 1858 May 26
  - Alexander Rives to Robert Rives, Jr.
    - Alexander Rives, C[arelon], to Robert Rives, Oakland 1848 Feb 14
      -- business
    - Alexander Rives to Robert Rives 1854 Apr 23
  - Cornelia Rives to Robert Rives, Jr. and Elizabeth Pannill Rives
    - Cornelia Rives, Richmond, to her father Robert Rives 1861 Feb 2
    - Cornelia Rives, Richmond, to her father Robert Rives 1861 Mar 24
    - Cornelia (Rives) Harrison, Richmond, to her mother Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives 1865 Dec 1
    - Cornelia (Rives) Harrison, Richmond, to her mother 1866 Feb 16
    - Cornelia (Rives) Harrison, Richmond, to her mother 1866 Feb 24
  - Elizabeth Pannill Rives to Cornelia Rives and Ella Rives
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia, in school in Richmond (10 letters) 1859-1860
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oakland, to her daughter [Cornelia] 1859 Nov 7
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia 1860 Jan 9
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia 1860 Feb 24
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia 1860 Apr 9
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter [Cornelia] 1860 Apr 29
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia 1860 May 16
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter [Cornelia] 1860 May 21
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia 1860 May 23
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter [Cornelia] 1860 June 10
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter [Cornelia] 1860 Oct 29
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia 1860 Oct 31
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia (Rives) Harrison (Mrs. Charles...), Richmond 1866 Feb 19
      -- financial; labor troubles
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Oak Land, to her daughter Cornelia (Rives) Harrison (Mrs. Charles...) 1866 Feb 24
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Campbell to her daughter, Cornelia (Rives) Harrison (Mrs. Charles...) 1868 July 20
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives to her daughter Ella n.d.
  - Elizabeth Pannill Rives to Robert Rives, Jr.
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Green Hill, to her husband Robert Rives 1841 Oct 15
    - Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Campbell Courthouse, to her husband Robert Rives, Lynchburg 1861 Feb 23
  - Margaret Cabell Rives and Pauline Cabell Rives to Robert Rives, Jr.
    - Margaret Cabell Rives, Oakridge, to Robert Rives, Jr. 1855 Dec 30
    - Pauline Cabell Rives, Orange, New Jersey, to Robert Rives, Jr. 1856 Feb 7
  - Robert Rives, Jr. to Elizabeth Pannill Rives
    - Robert Rives to Elizabeth Pannill, 1840
  - Robert Rives, Jr. to Elizabeth Pannill Rives
    - Robert Rives, Lynchburg, to his wife Elizabeth (Pannill) Rives, Green Hill 1841 Oct 13
      -- family news
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oak Ridge, to his wife, Green Hill, Campbell County, Virginia 1841 Oct 19
      -- family and local news; his plantations in Nelson County; the marriage of James P. Holcombe to Ann Watts, daughter of General Watts
    - W[illiam] C[abell] Rives, Washington, to Robert Rives, Jr., Oak Ridge near Livingston, Nelson County, Virginia 1841 June 27
      -- congratulations on his marriage
  - Robert Rives, Jr. to Elizabeth Pannill Rives
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oak Ridge, to his wife, Green Hill 1842 Aug 10
      -- family and farm
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Belle Mont, to his wife, Green Hill 1842 Aug 17
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oak Ridge, to his wife 1845 Mar 6
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oak Ridge, to his wife 1845 Mar 8
      -- extreme illness of his father
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Lynchburg, to his wife, Campbell County Courthouse 1845 Apr 22
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oak Ridge, to his wife 1845 Apr 25
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oakland, to his wife, Green Hill 1845 Oct 9
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oak Ridge, to his wife 1845 Oct 14
      -- personal and family news
    - Robert Rives, Green Hill, to his wife 1851 June 21
      -- death of her sister Ann
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife, Green Hill 1854 Oct 10
    - Robert Rives, Warren, Virginia, to his wife, Green Hill 1854 Oct 12
      -- wedding of Finny Gannt
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife, Green Hill 1854 Oct 14
      -- travelling instructions
  - Robert Rives, Jr. to Elizabeth Pannill Rives
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife 1858 Apr 27
    - Robert Rives, Jr., Oakland, to his wife 1858 Apr 29
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife 1859 June 4
      -- farm affairs
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife, Richmond 1859 Oct 25
      -- on travelling
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife, Richmond 1860 Apr 2
      -- family news; sunken freight boat
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife, c/o John D. Alexander, Campbell Courthouse 1860 Aug 9
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife 1860 Aug 18
      -- her visit to "Allegheny Springs"
    - Robert Rives, Oakland, to his wife 1860 Aug 21
      -- her visit to "Allegheny Springs"; danger of landslides of Virginia and Tennessee Railroads; death or Dr. Richard Thornton
  - William Cabell Rives to Robert Rives, Jr.
    - W[illiam]; C[abell] Rives, Castle Hill, to Robert Rives 1845 Apr 2
      -- father's estate
    - W[illiam]; C[abell] Rives, Castle Hill, to Robert Rives, Warren 1854 May 8
      -- regrets on latter's absence from an event [a wedding?]
    - W[illiam]; C[abell] Rives, Castle Hill, to [ ] 1864 Sep 9
      -- opinions on war and politics
  - Rives family letters miscellaneous
    - Robert Rives, Oak Ridge, to Robert Rives, Jr., Warren, Albemarle County 1843 July 11
      -- wheat and finances
    - M. Barrow, Locust Hill near Nashville, to George Rives 1845 July 2
      -- two runaway slaves
    - Pauline Pollard, Orange, New Jersey, to her brother Robert Rives 1856 Feb 7
    - Peggy Rives, Oakridge, to her brother Robert Rives, Oakland near Warren, Albemarle County 1875 Dec 30
    - Charles W. Page, Pittsburg, to Robert Rives, Oak Ridge, Nelson County n.d.
      -- brief description of Pittsburg
  - Letters to Cornelia Rives
    - Rosalie Harrison, Sherwood, to Cornelia Rives 1860 Apr 29
    - Rosalie Harrison, Sherwood, to Cornelia Rives 1864 July
    - K. M. Perkins, Afton, to Cornelia Rives 1864 Dec 5
      -- attitude toward war
    - Sallie W. L. [ ], Richmond, to Cornelia Rives ca. 1866 Apr 25
      -- mentioning visit of Grant to Richmond
    - [Rosalie Harrison], Sherwood, to [Cornelia Rives] n.d.
      -- the former's lost love
- Business and Legal Papers
  - Robert Rives, Jr. 1820 Oct 7
    -- law license, Virginia
  - -- discussion of Harrison's election, pro-Harrison; Hodgson's hopes for State Department appointment to Constantinople; marriage of Hugh Blair Grigsby to Mary Carrington 1840 Dec 12
  - -- bad roads, dull society due to families spending winters in R[ ] and Lynchburg 1841 Feb 2
  - "Remarks of the Honorable William C. Rives, of Virginia, on the Provisional Tariff Bill," delivered in the Senate of the United States on June 24, 1842 1842 June 24, Printed
  - "Inventory of the Estate, Real and Personal of Robert Rives, Deceased of Albemarle County, Virginia" n.d.